你以为你了解历史 其实你了解的只是历史的结局
You think you know a story, but you only know how it ends.
想要了解历史的真谛 你必须回到历史的开始
To get to the heart of the story, you have to go back to the beginning.
国王陛下到
His Majesty, the king.
各位大臣 各位议员 我们手头有很多工作要做
My lords and councillors, there is a great deal of work to do.
过去那些掌权的人对我背信弃义
In the past, those who held the reins of government deceived me.
不经我手 不经我允许 就擅自行事
Many things were done without my knowledge or my approval.
不过这些小动作以后统统都要废除
But such proceedings will stop in the future.
阁下您被委任为枢密院院长
Your Grace will be appointed president of the council.
与萨福克公爵共任
Jointly with the Duke of Suffolk.
谢陛下
Your Majesty.
短期内我们还要再开一次会
We shall convene again very shortly.
商讨与我们息息相关的大事
To discuss those matters which remain close to our hearts.
我们谈谈
A word.
虽然沃尔西不与我们共事
Although it pleases me much...
让我非常高兴…
...that Wolsey is no longer here among us, yet...
但是即便他不在场 他也没有引起你的不安吗？
Even in his absence, does he not cause you disquiet?
怎么会？
How so?
他只是被削权 并不是叛国罪
He was attaindered, but not for treason.
也就是说他还能苟活
Which means he still lives.
而且只要他还能苟延残喘 对王国 对你我都是一个威胁
And so long as he lives, he remains a danger both to the realm and to us.
他被流放到约克郡了 彻底失宠
He is far away in York. In disgrace.
我觉得您太危言耸听了
I think you exaggerate the danger.
但我觉得您并未明白
And I think that you don't understand it.
你很清楚 国王非常善变
The king, as you know, could easily change his mind.
如果他真改了主意 沃尔西又重返宫廷
And if he did, if Wolsey ever returned to this court...
你跟我都要担心他的复仇
...we would both have cause enough to fear his vengeance.
(约克郡 红衣主教沃尔西的教堂别院)
真受不了 必须得修修房顶了
This is intolerable. We must have the roof mended.
用什么修？谁来修？
With what and by whom?
我们既没钱也没有该死的仆人
We have no money and no bloody servants.
国王真打算让你如此潦倒吗？
Surely, the king never meant you to live so wretchedly?
毕竟你还是约克郡的大教主呢
After all, you are still archbishop of York.
可能也不是国王的错
Well, perhaps it's not the king's fault.
我不由得想起那古老的预言…
I have had cause to remember the old prophecy:
"当母牛骑上公牛 "神父们就要小心脑袋了"
"When the cow rideth the bull, then, priest, beware thy skull. "
你说安-博林是母牛？
You mean that cow Anne Boleyn?
的确如此
Indeed so.
正因如此我才给她写这封信
Which is why I'm writing her this letter.
她可是让我们穷困潦倒的罪魁祸首？
Even if she's the cause of all our misery?
是啊 既然她是罪魁祸首 她也会是灵丹妙药
Well, yes, since she's the cause, she can also be the cure.
如果我能说服她 我不是她的敌人 而是她的朋友
I just have to persuade her that I am not her enemy, but her friend.
我手上还有那封她写给我的信
I still have the letter in which she promises to reward me...
信里跟我保证只要她一旦登位 就会为我的辛劳和努力而报答我
...for all my pains and efforts at such time as she becomes crowned.
我恍惚记得
I seem to remember at the time...
那时你认为她的保证荒唐可笑
...you thought her promises rather amusing.
是的 也许确实如此
Well, yes, perhaps I did.
从那以后 我宁愿自己没有幽默感
Since then I have rather lost my sense of humour.
托马斯大人 我注意到在您的办公处所 没有任何的配饰
Sir Thomas, I notice you allow yourself none of the trappings of your office.
克伦威尔先生 我还没有虚荣到 四处彰显权势的地步
I'm not so vain as to display its power, Master Cromwell.
不过我跟你说 我却有意好好利用权势
But I tell you this, I fully intend to use it.
- 请问… - 您要讲自己的权利用于哪些方面吗？这儿
- May I ask to what effect? - Here, for example.
这儿有一份最近呈上剑桥的 告诫报告
Here is a report of a sermon recently given in Cambridge...
是一位名叫休-拉蒂莫的
...by a certain Hugh Latimer.
大学资深教员写的
A senior member of the university. And I quote:
拉蒂莫先生说"所有的基督教徒"
"Mr. Latimer said that holy scripture should be read in the English tongue...
"都应用英伦语言诵读圣经" "不论是神父还是俗人 "
...of all Christian people whether priest or layman.
他强烈抨击了为神像镀金的做法 认为那是"疯狂的膜拜"
He raged against the gilding of images...
"和迷信的魂祭 "
...the running of pilgrimages, and superstitious devotion.
他说"世间众人皆为神父"
He said that all men were priests...
"所谓的神父与教皇 吾等即可弃之 "
...and that we had no need for priests or popes on Earth. "
世道变了 克伦威尔先生
Times have changed, Master Cromwell.
我完全可以预见 对新奇和错误的教派 如此明目张胆的改革
Now I plainly see the risk and danger involved in such an open-door policy...
会有多么大的风险和危机
...towards these newfangled, erroneous sects.
您控诉所有的改革者为异教徒？
You condemn all Reformers as heretics?
沃尔西对他们太过纵容了
Wolsey was far too soft on them.
我可不准备这样
I intend not to be.
您会烧死他们吗？
Will you burn them?
"教皇以及神职人员所拥有的… "
"This belief that pope and clergy possess separate power...
"自主权和威信 恰恰与圣经相违背"
...and authority is contrary to scripture.
"国王才是上帝在世间的代表
The king is the representative of God on Earth...
他的法就是上帝的法令"
...and his law is God's law.
"统治者只对上帝一人聆讯
The ruler is accountable to God alone...
上帝授意所有子民都应顺从统治者
...and the obedience of his subjects is an obedience required by God.
"至于由教堂和教皇 来统领欧洲各国君王
For the Church and the pope to rule the princes of Europe...
"则不仅是奇耻大辱 更是冒上天之大不韪
...is not only a shame above all shames but an inversion of the divine order.
"每个王国都以上帝之名 有一位国王亦即有一部王法 "
One king and one law in God's name in every realm. "
这本书是为我所写 也为所有国王所写
This book is a book for me, and for all kings.
还有一些与此书类似的书
And there are other books like it.
详述教士们在陛下的领土之内
Books which detail the abuses of power, privileges...
滥用职权 贪婪餐腥的书
...the greed of the clergy in Your Majesty's realm.
也就是那些沃尔西 不想给您看到的书
Books which Wolsey deliberately kept hidden from you.
我真该看看这些书
I should like to read them.
如今我君权神授 亲自执政
Now I've taken power unto myself...
必要时我就得夜以继日 处理国事
...I shall work day and night if necessary to resolve things.
当然也包括废除我的婚姻
Including my annulment.
我向你发誓 一切将会改观
I swear to you now everything will be different.
国王陛下到
His Majesty the king.
- 查普大使 - 陛下
- Ambassador Chapuys. - Your Majesty.
我听说您是一位 能力超群 智慧过人的外交官
I hear you are a very able and intelligent diplomat.
我相信您和我一样 也留意到最近的宗教之争
Like me, I'm sure you're aware of all the new religious controversies.
当然了 我听说新的异教四处涌现
I know of some new heresies that have sprang up here and there, certainly.
只要教皇和他的红衣主教们 能放弃他们的虚架子和繁文缛节
If only the pope and his cardinals could set aside their vain pomp...
按照福音书和先父的意旨做事
...start living according to the precepts of the gospels the and early fathers.
我留意到陛下您
I am well aware Your Majesty...
正与教皇圣人进行辩论
...is in the midst of an argument with His Holiness.
我不是在说我自己
I'm not talking about myself.
阁下 路德抨击教士们的
You see, when Luther attacked the vice...
恶行与腐败 您该清楚 他是对的
...and corruption of the clergy, he was right.
他只停留到这个地步 未能毁掉圣餐这一类东西
Had he stopped, and not gone on to destroy the sacraments...
我会很高兴提笔为他声援
...and so on, I would have raised my pen in his defence...
而不是对他口诛笔伐
...rather than attacking him.
教会需要改革是显而易见的
The need for reformation in the Church is manifest.
一国之王有责任促进改革 就如我在我的领土之内所做的一切
The emperor has a duty to promote it. As do I in my own domain.
真高兴我们俩有机会交流意见
I'm glad we've had this opportunity to exchange opinions.
- 陛下 - 大使
- Your Majesty. - Ambassador.
- 我很奇怪你怎么会有这么多时间 - 做什么？
- I'm surprised you have so much time. - To do what?
- 无事可做 - 你说什么？
- To do nothing. - What are you saying?
你不应该在管理国事吗？
Aren't you supposed to be running the country?
我都丢给诺福克了 他经验老到
I leave that to Norfolk. He's had more practise.
再说 和各国大使会面真是无聊透顶
In any case, meetings with ambassadors, infinitely tedious.
他们都是谎话精 伪君子和老不死
They're all liars, hypocrites, and middle-aged men.
你更情愿他们是女人？
Would you prefer them to be women?
如果所有的大使都是漂亮女人
My friend, if all ambassadors were beautiful women...
我会夜以继日地为国操劳
...I'd be serving my country day and night.
- 我们来了 - 阁下
- Here we are. - Your Grace.
我来介绍我的护卫 这是凯瑟琳-布鲁克小姐
Let me present my ward, Miss Catherine Brooke.
- 这是安东尼-耐福特爵士 - 凯瑟琳小姐
- Sir Anthony Knivert. - Miss Catherine.
- 先生 - 安东尼是最优秀的骑士
- Sir. - Anthony's one of our finest horsemen.
除了我跌下来的时候
Except for when I fall off.
- 你散步愉快吗？- 是的 阁下
- You enjoying your walk? - Yes.
那好 我就不耽搁
Good. Then I shan't delay you any further.
你前行的兴致了
Put your back into it, lads.
- 一个小尤物 不是吗？- 确是尤物
- Pretty little thing, isn't she? - Indeed, she is.
我要娶她
I'm gonna marry her.
您曾被流放过对吧 费什先生？
You've been in exile, Mr. Fish?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
把我滞留在荷兰是沃尔西主教的意思
It was Cardinal Wolsey's pleasure to keep me in Holland...
他害怕我会说出真相
...for fear I might speak the truth.
那你为什么要试图归来？
So why did you try to return?
我觉得 随着红衣主教的倒台和遣走
I thought, sir, that with the cardinal fallen and sent away...
这个国家的境况会变好
...that circumstances in this country might be changed for the better.
氛围会更加宽容
More tolerant.
在这个国家你有朋友吗？
Do you have friends in this country?
- 当然了 我可是英国人 - 在宫廷呢？
- Of course, sir, as an Englishman. - At court?
你在宫廷有无朋友？
Do you have friends at court?
你不否认这是你的作品吧？
Do you deny you are the author of this work...
"乞丐的祈愿"
...A Supplication for the Beggars?
是的 先生
No, sir.
什么内容？
What is it?
请求陛下更正对教派
Sir, an appeal to His Majesty...
可怕而又诽谤性的迫害
...to redress many of the terrible and scandalous abuses of the Church.
你似乎建议的是 教会的真正目的是夺取贵族权力
You seem to suggest that the real aim of the Church...
夺取国王的尊贵与公信
...is to seize all power, lordship, obedience and dignity from the king.
事实上你更过分 你声称教会是叛党之源
In fact, you go further. You claim that the Church itself...
违抗国王之威名
...is a source of rebellion and disobedience against the king.
不是吗 费什先生？
Don't you, Mr. Fish?
还有这儿 费什先生
And here, Mr. Fish, if I may.
"对人民的苛捐杂税
You say that the exactions taken from the people...
不是献给了仁慈而又现世的君王
...are not given to a kind, temporal prince...
"而是冷酷而又残暴的
...but to "a cruel, devilish bloodsucker...
渴饮着殉教者和圣徒们血的嗜血者
...drunken in the blood of the martyrs and saints of Christ. "
真为你感到羞耻 费什先生
Shame on you, Mr. Fish.
替那些被你称为冷酷残暴的嗜血者…
For who are these cruel, devilish bloodsuckers...
但也同时是神圣教会的基督神父们 而感到羞耻
...but the anointed priests of our holy Church.
他们为我们指引通往天堂的路
Those who show us the way to heaven.
但你不再坚信这一点了 对吗 费什先生？
But then, you don't believe in that either, do you, Mr. Fish?
你是什么人？
Who are you?
我是一个虔诚的基督徒 永恒之乐的孩子
I'm a Christian man, the child of everlasting joy...
经历过上帝所赐予的苦难磨练
...through the merits of the bitter passion of Christ.
这就是虔诚圣悦的回答
This is the joyful answer.
也是异端之辞
It is also heresy.
这是怎么回事？她又出什么花招？
What is it? What has she done?
她穿着紫色
She is wearing purple.
紫色是王权的颜色
And purple is the colour of royalty.
有时我真希望
You know, I sometimes wish...
所有的西班牙人都葬身海底
...that all Spaniards were at the bottom of the sea.
博林女士
Mistress Boleyn...
您不该用这种话污蔑王后的尊贵
...you should not abuse the queen's honour with such language.
我根本不在乎凯瑟琳
I care nothing for Catherine.
我宁愿她吊死 也不愿尊称她为主人
I would rather see her hanged than acknowledge her as my mistress.
- 可以了吗？- 是的 陛下
- Is that it? - Yes, Your Majesty.
感谢上帝
Thank God.
什么事情 克伦威尔先生？
What is it, Mr. Cromwell?
陛下 我…
Your Majesty, I...
克伦威尔先生
Mr. Cromwell.
在我说话之前 我要请求陛下的宽容与原谅
I must beg Your Majesty's indulgence, and forgiveness, before I...
说下去
Go on.
最近我有事去了一趟沃尔瑟姆修道院
I had cause, recently, on a visit to Waltham Abbey...
与一位学识渊博的朋友倾谈
...to speak to a learned friend there.
我们聊到… 陛下的离婚大事
We spoke about Your Majesty's great matter.
我们总结道陛下的顾问不会…
We came to the conclusion Your Majesty's advisers...
可能不会以常见的
...might not, perhaps, be approaching the matter...
解决方式达成此事
...in the most convenient way to solve it.
- 你的意思是法庭裁决不可行？ - 是的
- You mean through the courts? - Yes.
是的 如陛下所知 国王凌驾于法律之上
As Your Majesty well knows, kings are set above the law.
他们只听上帝的旨意 上帝让国王们成为神子
They are answerable to God alone, who anointed them.
所以这似乎告诉我们 此事绝非关系到法律事宜
So it seems to us that the matter is not, and never has been, a legal one.
只关神权
It is a theological one.
但那样的话 谁来裁决此事？
But in that case, who should pass verdict upon it?
我们建议
We would suggest...
陛下在欧洲各大学院
...that Your Majesty canvass the opinion of theologians...
仔细研究神学家的观点
...at colleges around Europe.
他们的檄文会很快出炉
Their sentence would be pronounced...
略施小技就可执行
...and could be implemented with little industry.
只凭这简单的手段
And by that simple measure...
我相信陛下困扰许久的良知 会随之平静
...I trust that Your Majesty's troubled conscience might be pacified.
你能就你的观点写一篇文章吗？
Will you write a paper showing your argument?
- 如果陛下信任我这么做的话 - 不 我命令你这么做
- Lf Your Majesty trusts me to do so. - No, I command you to do so.
我还命令你以御史身份
Then I command you, as a royal agent...
探访欧洲各所大学
...visit the universities in Europe.
我要尽快得到神学者们的意见
I want the opinion of their theological faculties as soon as possible.
谢谢你 克伦威尔先生
Thank you, Mr. Cromwell.
还有时间让您放弃异教 菲什先生
There's still time to recant of your heresy, Mr. Fish.
只要你承认你的观点都是受人误导 是罪恶的
If you acknowledge that your opinions were misguided, evil...
是违背上帝法则的
...contrary to the law of God...
这样你就可以减少痛苦 否则你就会痛不欲生
...then you will be spared the great pains you must otherwise endure.
我请求你意识到自己的罪行
I beg of you, acknowledge your sins.
上帝会重新张开怀抱欢迎你回来
God will welcome you back into his fold.
放弃吧
Recant.
你还有机会
Recant, you still have a moment.
我的主是我的守护者 我别无所求
The Lord is my shepherd, I can want nothing.
他指引我至青草地上 他指引我至清泉水边
He feedeth me in green pastures, he leadeth me to fresh waters.
我虽行入死亡的阴影
Though I should walk now in the valley of the shadow of death...
也不畏惧邪恶 因为你与我同在
...yet I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.
你的权杖 你的盾牌 都赐我慰藉
Thy staff and thy sheep, they comfort me.
在我敌人面前 你为我摆设筵席
Thou preparest a table for me, against mine enemies.
你用油膏神化我的头 使我福杯满溢
My head Thou anoints with oil, and filleth my cup full.
哦 我一生一世 必有恩惠慈爱伴随于我
Oh, let thy loving-kindness and mercy follow me all the days of my life...
我且要住在主的殿中 直到永远
...that I mayest dwell in the Lord's house for ever.
我有些事情要对你说
I have something I want to say to you.
我决定册封你和你的家族
I have decided to ennoble you and your family.
你被册封为威尔彻和奥蒙德伯爵
You are to be created Earl of Wiltshire and Ormonde...
同时我委任你为掌玺大臣
...and I am also appointing you Lord Privy Seal.
乔治被封位罗彻福爵士
George will become Lord Rochford...
同时成为枢密院一员
...and be made a member of council.
陛下 我受宠若惊
Your Majesty, I'm lost for words.
这真是皇恩浩荡
Your bounty is unceasing.
我同时对克伦威尔先生寄予厚望
I also have high hopes for Mr. Cromwell.
我很高兴 他是我们家族的一个朋友
I'm glad. He is a friend of the family.
你知道他的论文
You know his thesis.
我要你出访博洛尼亚 拜见教皇和罗马皇帝
I want you to visit the pope and the emperor at Bologna.
去呈上我们新的申请
I want you to put to them our new case.
请告诉我 您没有放弃希望
Please tell me you are not losing hope.
真的 我…
It is true, I...
我常常幻想国王
I had always fancied that the king...
在追逐风流一段时间之后 仍然能回心转意
...after pursuing his course for some time, would turn away...
想臣服他的良知 改变他的心意
...would yield to his conscience, and change his purpose...
就像以前他常做的那样
...as he has done so often before.
我曾坚信用我全部的身心 让他回归理性
I believed with all my heart that he would return to reason.
但如今 我…
But now I...
夫人 我为您祈祷 不要放弃
Madam, I pray you. Don't give way.
不 阁下 我从未放弃
No, Excellence. I shall never give way.
谢谢你赐予我父亲的一切
Thank you for what you have done for my father.
以及我家族的荣耀
For my whole family.
以后还会有的…
There's more.
我把沃尔西在约克郡的老宅 做了些改变
I've made alterations to Wolsey's old palace at York Place.
你说过你喜欢那里…
You said you liked it.
我要把那个地方送给你
I am giving it to you.
怎么了？
What is it?
我惹你不高兴了吗？
Have I made you unhappy?
没有
No.
如果你不再钟情于我 我才会伤心
I would only be unhappy if you ever stopped loving me.
那要伦敦首先容融化流入泰晤士河
London would have to melt into the Thames first.
这就是为安妮准备的一切了
It is everything now for the lady Anne?
托马斯先生 这有没有让你觉得像一场喜筵？
Sir Thomas, does this not remind you of a wedding feast?
好像就差一个牧师
It seems to me that nothing is wanted but a priest...
给他们佩戴戒指 宣布誓言了
...to give away the nuptial rings and pronounce the blessing.
但愿不要这样
God forbid that should happen.
其实这不关我事
It's none of my business.
我作为大臣的新工作就是竭力
My new job as chancellor...
吸引基督教徒的兴趣
...will be to do my utmost to contend for the interests of Christendom.
也许你没想到
Perhaps the king's Majesty...
国王陛下更倾向于改革者
...is more inclined towards the Reformers than you know.
我不这么看
I don't think so.
显然我比你更了解他
I know him better than you do, Excellence.
他最深的本能传统而坚实
His deepest instincts are traditional and faithful.
他也许会放言与罗马断交
He may threaten to break with Rome...
但我不认为他会那么做
...but I don't think he will ever do so.
希望你是对的
I hope you are right.
否则后果将无法想象
The consequences would be unthinkable.
事态正如您期望的发展 大人
Everything seems to move in your favour, Your Grace.
我有个坏消息
I have bad news.
我听说国王送给
I happen to know that the king...
沃尔西一尊他的玉石雕像
...has sent Wolsey an intaglio portrait of himself.
那又怎么样？
So?
这通常是示好的表现
So it is traditionally a sign of goodwill.
也许这预示着他们将重修旧好
It may presage a reconciliation.
国王的小礼物只是为了 让自己良心得到安慰
A small gift to ease the king's conscience is hardly a sign...
并不代表失宠的主教还能恢复名望
...that the bishop of York will be restored to his former glory.
换个角度想
Think of it this way.
从天堂坠落的圣人 有人邀请他回去么
When Satan fell from heaven, was he ever invited back?
你就是啊
You were.
怀亚特先生 听说您接受了克伦威尔先生的庇护
I see that you have accepted patronage from Mr. Cromwell, Mr. Wyatt.
世界真透明啊
How very transparent the world is.
塔利斯 我这么做有错么？
But was I wrong to do so, Tallis?
是的 我觉得有 你应该靠你自己
I think so. Yeah. You should be your own man.
别傻了 塔利斯 在这个坠落的世界
Don't be a fool, Tallis. You won't survive long in this slippery world...
没有靠山的人是站不住的
...without the support of a great man.
你觉得克伦威尔能作靠山？
You think Mr. Cromwell is a great man?
不 我感觉他未来大有前途 记住我说的
No, I think he's a coming man. Mark my words.
直跟你说了吧 我的确上了她
For what it's worth, I did fuck her.
托马斯 怎么了？
What is it, Thomas?
我收到了回信
I have had a reply to my letter.
博林夫人寄来的？
From Mistress Boleyn?
她怎么说？
What did she say?
她不想在国王那替我说话
That she will not speak to the king on my behalf.
我们的希望破灭了
Then our hopes are over.
不
No. No, no.
我想给一个更有权利的女士写封信
I have resolved to write to another lady...
一个比那个可恶的娼妓更为尊贵
...who is far greater, far greater than that mischievous whore.
更有可能发发慈悲的人
And far more likely to be kind.
夫人 国王来了
Madam, the king is here.
来 请坐
Please. Be seated.
陛下
Majesty.
我听说您身体欠佳 于是过来探望
I came because I heard you were unwell.
医生给你放点血也是必要的
And that it was necessary for the physician to have bled you.
- 你现在感觉怎么样？ - 很好
- How are you feeling now? - I am very well.
我很好 感谢陛下的关心
Your Majesty is kind to show concern.
我们的女儿怎么样了？
How is our daughter?
她用漂亮的拉丁文给我写信说 她每天都在练习三拍舞了
She writes to me in perfect Latin and tells me she dances the galliards...
弹得一手好琵琶 让人们都欢愉满足
...and can play the lute much to everyone's satisfaction and joy.
- 你应当引以为傲 - 我的确为她骄傲
- You should be proud of her. - I am proud of her.
你应该请她入宫
You ought to invite her to court.
可以看她唱歌娱乐
You could watch her dancing and playing.
- 会让你很高兴的 - 凯瑟琳…
- It might please you. - Catherine, I...
我听说你派了几个代表出国
I hear that several of your agents...
去研究离婚的神学主张了
...have been sent abroad to canvass theological opinion about the divorce.
你能找出一个支持你的学者
For every scholar that votes for you...
我就能找出1000个支持我的
...I could find a thousand who would vote for me.
大人们…
My lords...
每天我都被强迫看这些表示不满
...every day I'm forced to read new reports of dissatisfaction...
说我的国家混乱低效的报告
...confusion and delays throughout my kingdom.
我们国库空虚
My exchequer is empty...
正在以高价利息从外借款
...and we are borrowing money at a biting rate.
你们是议会的大臣
Your Graces are presidents of this council...
这个问题我从没听过你们的建议
...and yet I hear nothing from you on these matters.
其他问题也一样
Nor any other matter.
陛下 您必须宽恕我们
Your Majesty must forgive me...
是的 我知道我必须原谅你 我一直在宽恕你
Yes, I know. I must always forgive you.
但我已经厌倦了宽恕你
But I grow tired of forgiving you!
我给了你一切 甚至自称王子的权力
I have given you everything, including the right to call yourself prince!
我得到什么回报了呢？
And what do I get in return?
以前我认为主教爱慕虚荣 自私贪婪
I used to think the cardinal vain, self-serving and greedy...
就像你们跟我说的
...just as you told me.
现在我体会到了他肩负的重担… 毫无怨言
But now I understand the burden he carried, uncomplainingly.
陛下也不能忘了他监守自盗
Your Majesty should not forget that he also stole from you...
他对法国的效忠甚至
...and he served the interests of the French...
多于英国
...even above those of England.
你是这么想的么 托马斯？
Is that what you think, Thomas?
的确主教虚荣至极
It is certainly true that the cardinal was vainglorious beyond measure.
这极度的腐化了他
It did him tremendous harm...
使他滥用上帝赐予他的天赋
...and made him abuse the considerable gifts God gave him.
可是他在治理国家方面
And yet he is a better man than any of you...
比你们都强
...for managing this kingdom's matters.
- 我会跟他谈谈 - 是 你必须要跟他谈
- I will talk to him. - Yes, you must.
陛下 查普大使参见
Ambassador Chapuys, Your Majesty.
大使
Ambassador.
- 我这有给您的一封信 - 罗马皇帝给我的？
- I have a letter for Your Majesty. - From the emperor?
不 沃尔西主教给您的
No. From Cardinal Wolsey.
太… 太奇怪了 他说什么？
This is so strange. Do you know what it says?
主教希望您和他 包括罗马和罗马皇帝之间
The cardinal is offering to create a rapprochement...
能够重新和解
...between you and he, the emperor, and Rome.
罗马教皇布告的到达 就是政变的信号
The coup would be signalled by the arrival of a papal edict...
迫使亨利放弃安妮博林 回复他的婚姻
...ordering Henry to leave Anne Boleyn and return to his marriage.
罗马皇帝会给他经济和道义支持
The emperor will offer his financial and moral support...
并让沃尔西重新做回议政大臣
...and insist that Wolsey be reinstated as chancellor.
你认为这一方法有效吗？
Do you think it could work?
红衣主教拥有最多的就是智慧
The cardinal is nothing if not ingenious.
我希望您成立新的议会
I want you to set up a new parliament.
这些大事需要解决
Important things need to be done.
正如我的国库空虚一事
My exchequer is empty, for one thing.
我会谨遵您的命令
I will do as Your Majesty commands.
但我要指出 这个新国会…
But I must warn you that you may not find this parliament...
也许不会像以前的那个一样忠诚于您
...as compliant as those before.
为什么？
How so?
虽然我一直与那些
Well, though I must confess to being amongst those...
要求容忍和言论自由的人一起
...who called for greater tolerance and freedom of speech...
但恐怕如果陛下仁慈地给予了这些自由
...I fear that the freedom so given by Your Majesty's kindness...
那它们将被滥用
...is now openly abused.
国家内对于宗教问题…
There are many dissenting voices in the kingdom...
有很多不同的议论
...chiefly on religious matters.
都是在要求改革
There are calls for a reformation.
托马斯 你烧死了多少人？
How many have you burned, Thomas?
6个
Six.
都是按法律规程 有必要的… 并且处理妥当
All lawful, necessary and well done.
处理妥当？
Well done?
是的 哈利
Yes, Harry.
他说什么？
What did he say?
说了很多
Well, in so many words...
说他更倾向于宽恕沃尔西
...he told me that he was inclined to pardon Wolsey...
重新宠信他
...and restore him to royal favour.
你怎么回答的？
And what did you say?
我同意国王的观点 主教的确有很多才能
I agreed with His Majesty that the cardinal had many talents.
你说了什么？
You did what?
我同意国王的观点 主教的确有很多才能
I agreed with the king that His Eminence had many talents.
难以置信
I cannot believe this.
你从未想过如果他重新掌权
Have you not spoken yourself...
对我们每个人将会做出
...of the terrible vengeance he would exact on us...
多么可怕的报复吗？
...if he ever again had the power?
或许你不认为"复仇" 也是他的众多"才能"之一
Or perhaps you don't think vengeance to be one of his many talents.
我当然明白
I do indeed.
所以我才故意顺应国王的意愿
Which is why I cultivate the king's good graces.
陛下您肯定乐意知道 万众向往的
Your Majesty will be pleased to know that the University of Paris...
巴黎大学已经声明要助您一臂之力
...the greatest prize of all, has declared in your favour.
意大利呢？
And Italy?
我必须要说 那边的学院已经瓦解
I confess that the universities there are divided.
但是帕多瓦 佛罗伦萨和威尼斯 的学院都支持陛下您
But Padua, Florence and Venice have all declared for Your Majesty.
西班牙呢？凯瑟琳的国家
Spain? Catherine's country?
西班牙反对
Spain is against.
你很惊讶么？
Are you surprised?
还有你 大人
And you, my lord.
你见到罗马皇帝和教皇了么？
Did you get to see the emperor and His Holiness?
他们怎么样？
How are they?
陛下 罗马皇帝拒绝见我
Your Majesty, the emperor refused to see me.
教皇呢？
And His Holiness?
教皇只是让我把这部布告带给陛下
The pope simply gave me this edict, to bring to Your Majesty.
布告怎么说？
What does it say?
布告上要求您
The edict instructs Your Majesty...
将安-博林女士逐出宫廷
...to order Lady Anne Boleyn to leave your court.
在教皇制元老院的裁定下
It refuses to allow Your Majesty permission to remarry...
他们拒绝批准陛下您离婚一案
...while the papal curia is deciding Your Majesty's case.
怀亚特先生
Mr. Wyatt.
- 我很忙 - 这个东西你该看看
- I am busy. - There is someone you should see.
- 现在不行 怀亚特先生 - 这事关主教大人
- Not now, Mr. Wyatt. - It concerns the cardinal.
大人 有什么能效劳的？
Your Excellency. What can I do for you?
大人 我有一事相求
My Lord, I would ask you a very great favour.
在这么一个混乱的年代
These are troubled times.
貌似在一些地区
It seems to me that in certain quarters...
对神圣教堂的抱怨和敌意
...there is now a blatant and open hostility to our holy Church.
- 正如我们在德国所发现的情形 - 你希望我做什么？
- As we discovered in Germany... - And what do you expect me to do?
我希望您能使用 您在宫廷和这里的强大影响力
I beg you to use the great influence you have here at court...
把英国从灾难和毁灭的边缘拉回来
...to pull England back from the brink of catastrophe and ruin.
看在主和他的信徒们给我们的恩泽上
For the love we all bear for Christ and his apostles.
什么信徒？
What apostles?
我不相信主和信徒 即使是圣彼得
I don't believe Christ had apostles, not even Saint Peter.
那些都是以上帝之名假意遵从她的旨意
Those men were all charlatans...
的骗子和伪君子
...who pretended to follow Christ and speak in his name.
他们把教堂构建在谎言之上
And they built a Church upon their lies.
上帝之母啊
Mother of God.
大人… 大人… 十分感激
Your Honour, Your Honour, so grateful.
先生 他是奥古斯蒂尼
Sir, this is Augustus de Augustinis.
托马斯-沃尔西的私人医生
A private physician to Thomas Wolsey.
沃尔西 你了解他么？
Wolsey? What do you know about him?
先生 我知道沃尔西求助于罗马皇帝和…
Sir, I know that Wolsey sought the help of the emperor and the p...
- 罗马教皇？- 是的 大人
- The pope? - Yes, your honour...
教皇 反对… 陛下
...His Holiness the pope. Against His Majesty.
- 他们有联络？ - 是的…
- They communicated? - Yes, yes, yes.
还有谁？
And who else?
沃尔西和凯瑟琳女王串通
Wolsey conspired with Queen Catherine...
他说这是他唯一能…
...because he said it was the only way that he could be...
- 重拾权力的方法 - 是啊… 是啊…
- Restored to power. - Yes.
国王必须知道这些
The king must know of this.
你知道真相了 你一定要阻止他
Now you know the truth, you must act against him.
他和他的牧师教士认为
He and his fellow priests and prelates...
他们能控制您的王国
...think they can control Your Majesty's realm.
认为他们比你更为位高权重
That they are higher than you.
遵从教皇的旨意绝对不是
And by taking instruction from the pope...
沃尔西身为驻外使节的本分
...was not Wolsey acting as an agent of a foreign country?
自以为是的教皇
The presumption of the pope...
认为他能指挥你… 告诉你该干什么
...thinking he could tell you, you, what to do.
所有人 不许动 这是国王的旨意
Wolsey, sir. In the name of the king.
- 起来 - 从床上下来
- Get up. - Get out of bed.
- 不 不 - 不管他的事
- No, no. - He's done nothing.
托马斯-沃尔西 国王下令
Thomas Wolsey, you are arrested by order of the king...
以高度叛国罪名逮捕你
...and charged with high treason.
你将被转押到伦敦 在那里接受审讯
You will be taken to London, where you will be tried.
- 走开 琼 - 守卫
- There, there, Joan. - Guards.
不要哭 不要为我哭泣 我求求你
No tears. No tears for me, I beg you.
原谅我
Forgive me.
没能给你留下些什么 值得你记住我的东西
For you have not much to remember me by.
不 我一生和每件事都是你给的回忆
No. I have a life and everything in it to remember you by.
守卫 铐住他
Guards, shackle him.
布兰登啊 布兰登
Well, well, Brandon.
如果我效忠上帝犹如 效忠国王一样的话
If I had served God as diligently as I served the king...
他就不会在我两鬓斑白时抛弃我
...he would not have given me up in my grey hairs.
走
Move on.
琼…
Joan.
琼
陛下 很遗憾通知您
I regret to have to inform Your Majesty...
我不能继续在这个宫里 为罗马皇帝效劳了
...that I can no longer continue to serve the emperor at this court.
这里对于一切神圣和真实的事情 充满了愤恨
There is so much hatred here for everything that is sacred and true...
那些厚颜无耻大肆宣扬此言论的人 让我无法留在此地
...that those who speak brazenly of it have driven me away.
这不怪你
You are not to blame.
你一直在用你的智慧和仁慈为我效力
You have always served me with wisdom and kindness.
我永生难忘
I will not forget it.
给我的外甥带好
Send my love to my nephew.
我会告诉皇帝您的处境
I will inform His Highness of your plight...
告诉他国王陛下对您 怨恨和恶劣的态度
...and of the malice and unkindness of His Majesty towards you.
是的 告诉他
Yes, tell him.
还要告诉他 我对这个国家的爱 正如我对他本人的爱一样
But this also, for the love I bear this country as well as him.
他不能对国王陛下和他的百姓动武
He must not think to use force against His Majesty or his people.
否则 那将是违背良知 违背上帝的罪行
It would be a sin against my conscience and against God.
主啊 我们本该经常倾谈 可却未能做到
Lord, we have not spoken as long or as often as we should.
但我却总在忙其他的事
I have often been about other business.
如果我想要请求宽恕 我可以向您要求…
If I wanted forgiveness, I should ask for it...
但我的所作所为
...but for all that I have done...
以及所有我还未做到的事情 我是无法被您原谅的
...and for all that I am yet to do, there can be no forgiveness.
但我认为我并不是个邪恶的人
And yet, I think, I'm not an evil man.
虽然邪恶之人大声祈祷
Though evil men pray louder...
寻求忏悔
...and seek penance...
认为他们比我距离天堂更近
...and think themselves closer to heaven than I am.
我看不见天堂的大门了
I shall not see its gates, Lord.
也听不见您挽救我的箴言…
Nor hear your sweet words of salvation.
我看到了永生 我发誓…
I have seen eternity, I swear...
但那只是一场梦 天亮后就烟消云散
...but it was in a dream, and in the morning all was gone.
我清楚了解我自己是怎样的人
I know myself for what I am.
我将献上我卑微的灵魂 祈求您的宽恕
And I throw my poor soul upon your forgiveness...
我清楚的知道…
...in the full knowledge that I deserve none...
我不配得到您的任何慈爱
...at your loving hands.
欢迎… 到地狱来
Welcome to hell.
啊
Ahh
克伦威尔先生
Mr. Cromwell.
陛下…
Majesty...
沃尔西主教死了
Cardinal Wolsey is dead.
万分遗憾
I'm sorry to hear that.
我希望他还活着
I wish he'd have lived.
他怎么死的？
How did he die?
自我了断…
Took his own life.
这件事不能张扬 明白么？
No one must ever know. Do you understand?
不能让任何人知道
No one. Never.
等我射完这轮 我们再好好谈
I'll finish my game, and we'll talk.
走吧
Go.
走
托马斯先生 我刚听说了
Sir Thomas, I have just heard.
国王下令 15位资深牧师
By His Majesty's order, 15 senior clergymen...
由于承认沃尔西的权威而被捕
...have been arrested for recognising Wolsey's authority.
议会还有一项法令
There is also a statute before parliament...
承认在当前各种适宜上以及精神上…
...which recognizes in matters temporal and spiritual...
国王的命令凌驾于法律 并且只听从上帝的教诲
...the king is above the law and shall give account to God alone.
我们能做什么？
What can be done?
我想起来沃尔西曾经告诉我
I am reminded of something Wolsey once told me.
只可以告诉国王他该做什么 而不是他能做什么
That I should only tell the king what he ought to do not what he could do.
如果狮子知道了自己的力量 就没人能控制它
"For if the lion knows his own strength, no man could control him. "
我们站在深渊的边缘…
We're standing on the edge of the abyss.
上帝知道我们要遭遇什么
God knows what shall become of us.
我想要你
I want you.
- 我忍不住了 - 不 你不能
- I'm gonna come. - No, you mustn't.
或许你能想出一种方法 让他对你的兴趣… 更加持久？
Perhaps you could imagine a way to keep his interest more prolonged?